So
a question
someone asked.
So it seems that other people generally
enjoy life through its ups and downs. Um
and um I have often kind of had well
issues with it.
the fact that you know practice feels
like you have to be giving up stuff um
renouncing but then you look around at
the people genuinely happy enjoying life
>> um
going in those directions. So, um, some
of our videos resonate with me. Uh, but
it's like overall it feels like, well,
this person is asking a question.
They're not quite ready
to give up the obvious joys and
pleasures and ups and downs of life that
everybody around them is very happy
about and enjoys them.
So they say that they want at least to
try to experience life like everybody
else um without being caught up in irrational
um without being caught up in irrational
thoughts and emotions. So it kind of
seems that it's important to become
normal >> so to speak before you can practice.
>> so to speak before you can practice.
>> And if they were to take it on now
practice of giving up stuff that they
still haven't quite experienced in that
sense it feels like they would just fall
apart. So any advice?
>> Well, what's the problem with having
irrational thoughts and like why do you
have that value and why does it stop
there? >> Can you explain that?
>> Can you explain that?
>> So irrational thoughts like for example
what could you describe as that you lost
something, somebody died?
>> Well, I think the problem is that
painful. Yeah, you would know. You would
know I don't want my mind to be
revolving around this. I would like to I
would like to let go of it.
>> And yet it keeps doing that.
>> Yeah.
>> So then if that's your value, which you
clearly said it is, then you want to
recognize being like those other people
engaging in normal things makes it
impossible that you won't have
irrational tendencies
because >> well those are all ups and downs of
>> well those are all ups and downs of
life.
>> Yeah. So you
>> so sometimes it's up sometimes down.
>> So [clears throat] you will have to as a
result of cultivating sensuality
experience irrationality of your own
mind, experience pain, experience the
exact same things that you said you
don't want to have
>> because of which you're interested in
the practice. So to the extent that you
have sensuality, you won't be able to
have freedom from irrationality, freedom
from pressure, freedom from
>> internal obsessions. So you want to
recognize that and keep that in mind
because well then it becomes up to you
to decide how much of how much freedom
do you actually want
>> because that will determine how much you
have to give up
>> right so yeah so let's say I want
freedom but
the pressure towards
experiencing what other people
experience namely sensuality obviously
ly uh enjoying life
um getting kind of as I said interacting
with life is just too much to handle.
>> Mhm. [snorts] So on one end yes I
understand that the root of the problem
is the irrational mind suffering and all
of that and that root is fundamentally
fueled by engaging with the world and
by engaging with the world and
sensuality but as of now at this stage
that recognition of what the practice is
is just too weak
>> against the pressure of being normal how
the person said
>> so can I just go and be normal and
experience everything and practice later
or what what do I do?
Or do I just grind my teeth and maybe go
mad and completely break apart, have a
breakdown and then simply dismiss the
whole direction of training forever?
>> Well, [snorts]
>> it's just too much.
>> Yeah.
>> What do I do when it's too much?
>> [snorts]
>> Well, when it's not too much, you re
When it is too much, you recognize
there are things that won't be too much
that you could still do that would still
take you less into the direction of
sensuality. >> Uhhuh. So
>> Uhhuh. So
try and keep an eye not go as far.
>> Yeah.
>> Not fall as far.
>> Because you're not neutral. Your desires
are proliferating.
>> Mhm.
>> When you engage with them. So if you
just blanket accept I'll go with it,
you're not going to stay like 10 years
later having the same level of desire
>> as when you started. You're actually
going to have ma made it even harder
>> to give it up. So essentially, yeah, if
you're not willing to take on the
practice, well, try to
actually stay where you are by by
restraining further proliferation rather
than just going with it fully.
>> So you're saying if you can't go forward
in the right sense of practice, at least
don't go backward.
>> Exactly.
>> At least don't cover up where forward
is, even if you can't do it right now.
>> Yeah.
Um
so that's the the precept of for example
often translated as uh misconduct in
regard to sexual pleasures and people
usually interpret it as well as long as
I'm not um cheating on my partner.
>> I'm not doing this.
>> But the poly very clearly says
misconduct in regard to sensual pleasure
not Yeah.
>> Yeah. So
that means you will want to keep an eye
on
are those sensual things that you're
engaging with even if they seem
relatively harmless.
How much of an animalistic obsession is
building up behind them
>> that like you would be willing to even
forgo forward thinking about
consequences >> and the the the overall like patience
>> and the the the overall like patience
and and future rewards for the sake of
this thing that I need to get right now.
>> Right. In other words, how far back you
choose to fall.
>> Yeah.
So in this specific scenario, this um
with so when the person kind of knows
what the practice entails,
but they just don't want to do it,
they don't feel ready to do it.
They should um well make themselves
ready gradually.
>> Yeah. through. So, so yes, they know
they'll engage with sensuality because
they haven't built up the restraint and
the value. They know it will offer a
relief. >> They know it will be pleasant. They know
>> They know it will be pleasant. They know
that doesn't matter how much they read
about the danger, they will they're not
going to see it.
So what you're saying what they should
do in that kind of scenario where they
will inevitably fail in terms of
precepts and celibacy they should
prevent themselves from falling too far.
>> So consider the implications secondary
implications of your impending failure
that you will willingly choose because
the mind is weak and go back to
addiction and so on
>> and then try and minimize the distance
that you would have to come back from
it. And you're saying that's what
kisumiacha is.
>> Yeah. Yeah. It's it's uh looking at your
intentions already,
>> how obsessive, passionate and and um
unrestrained they are.
>> So could you give some practical example
[sighs] of that
of that
in terms of yeah like say central
design? [clears throat]
So what would be okay either way it's a
as we said it's a choosing to kind of go
back to centrality or choosing to fail
but what would constitute successful
kamisumachara where is the line
>> you mean at which point would they
>> yeah so the out of the five pre Yeah
exactly when would be against the
precept when it becomes misconduct in
sensuality that precept because it's
obviously vague yeah Well,
as you
>> with some examples,
>> uh well, concrete example would be uh
the very common modern addiction towards
pornography, um masturbation,
um masturbation,
>> things that
you see that when you give into them,
the result is
more pressure to keep engaging with
them. >> Like,
>> Like,
>> well, that's inevitable. That's going to
happen whenever you touch sensuality.
But where is the line when okay now I
gave in within the third precept of a
you know non-practicing household there
>> uh well trying to practice householder
it's not necessarily non-practicing but
when is the within the precept and when
is oh this is now against the third
precept
either way it's going to feel you know
you gave in sensuality but when does it
become against the third precept in the
five precepts
Like giving in is inevitable.
Giving in to some extent is within the
third householder precepts.
>> Mhm.
>> But crossing that extent is against
how can you when do how do you know how
can you confess the third like breaking
of the third precept of layman's
precept? Well, but that's the thing like it's how
Well, but that's the thing like it's how
would you categorize
different levels of of obsession
objectively? >> So, it's about obsession.
>> So, it's about obsession.
>> Yeah.
>> Where's the line?
>> Again, giving it once, you'll be doing
it out of obsession.
>> Yeah.
>> Giving it 10 times, it's out of
obsession. >> Can I give 10 times or is five times the
>> Can I give 10 times or is five times the
line or two times? Where's the line? Is
there a line?
>> Well, yeah. um
how easy would it be for you to stop
that specific thing? is does it become
an addiction
or do you still recognize okay I could
still even if I have desire for it I
could still choose not to do it
>> but obviously you can't because then
you'll be actually celibate and
practicing towards the dhamma rightly
within the eight precepts
>> yeah but [clears throat] um
there is a difference between like okay
I'll give into sensuality either way
>> and this specific thing now I can't live
without
But how is it against the precinct? How
is that misconduct?
>> Well, because it takes you towards a
level of not just overall dependence but
being like an animal where an animal is
>> but would just giving in once make you
an animal.
>> Uh well, no. It's like because
>> so then it's fine. The difference is a
human can have a desire for something,
recognize for whatever reason I shouldn't engage
for whatever reason I shouldn't engage
with it because it's going to lead to
greater harm in the future. But then an
animal No, I know that. But that's
you're still talking on the universal
level. That is universally true for
giving in once or 100 times. But we're
talking about a precept that technically
allows you to give in to some extent
because you're unable to be celibate and
actually practice like uh the noble
path. you're working towards it. So
you're using five precepts to train
towards the eight precepts. And they do
factually allow you some extent of
giving in.
>> Mhm.
>> Where is the line? You can't apply the
universal truth or you're going to
because it's true whether you give in
once or 100 times. Universal principle
is yes, you're you're giving into
sensuality and stuff. And from that
universal point of view, it's all wrong.
>> But for somebody who gradually trains
towards the eight precepts,
>> some extent is allowable. What is that
extent? How can the person for
themselves develop discern the criteria of where
develop discern the criteria of where
the extent of kamisumichachara is?
>> Well, yeah. I mean that's the thing.
It's I would see it as the extent of the
obsession. >> But how can you quantify that as a as a
>> But how can you quantify that as a as a
as a measure that somebody would be able
to tell like you said, "Oh, I confess it
because I saw that it crossed that
specific line."
>> Mhm. So the extent of obsession.
>> Yeah. But so get back to that and maybe
what would be say like a a daily example
of somebody how they go about
in regard to
keeping the extent of obsession in
check.
So if like just imagine yourself like
say you want to you want to do something
during the day there is a desire there
is a compulsion there's pressure to give
in
as I said you you are self-aware you
know that you need to work towards the
eight precept you can't just overnight
undertake it all so you know you will
give in
>> how do you keep yourself in check and
that's already an obsession it's already
coming out of obsession so how do you
keep yourself in
whereby that obsession that you know you
will give in does not become the
obsession that now violates kamisum
chachara >> well yeah I mean I guess you could come
>> well yeah I mean I guess you could come
up with various
measures like can you postpone it
>> okay so yeah that's one practical way
>> so that's why I meant with an animal
like an animal has to give in at that
very moment
>> right there and then
>> there is no like
>> so can you postpone it can I
[clears throat] can I wait a bit Yeah.
>> What else?
>> Could you have something else?
>> So if I can't postpone it, if it feels
[clears throat] like I can't postpone
it, would then even giving in once be
against Kamisumachara.
>> If it is the extent of obsession as
measure then yes.
>> Yeah. It would exactly
>> Yeah.
>> Because there is no quantity. Even if
there were quantity basically written
within Kisumach.
>> Yeah.
>> Uh
it wouldn't serve the practical uh uh
purpose of training.
>> And that's exactly why even being
celibate can still be on the level of
>> silabata paramasa
>> because again you're not training in it.
>> You're not taking on those values.
You're just not doing this
>> and and abstaining from that. So
[clears throat]
even if you give in
or uh within the precepts of Kamisum
Mishachara, you could recognize okay somebody might
you could recognize okay somebody might
actually give in multiple do certain
things multiple times.
>> And still not necessarily be against
Kamisumach. But on different occasion the same thing
But on different occasion the same thing
depending on the level of obsession
>> the animality of the mind the obsession
behind it it's like even giving once
would be misconduct in sensuality.
>> So it's that was the point you can't
quantify it by any external measure.
>> Yeah.
>> But you can quantify it by recognizing
the extent of the pressure
>> the the the extent of the urgency.
[clears throat]
>> So you said can you postpone it? Yeah.
Are there any other practical
considerations person questions,
reflections they can do again to clarify
[clears throat] where the line is?
>> Could you do something else to appease
that pressure rather [clears throat]
than that specific thing?
>> So would
would an alternative to that which you
want satisfy the desire? Yeah,
satisfy the desire? Yeah,
>> less harmful you could say, but
>> less harmful alternative.
>> Anything else?
>> Is there any even mundane negative
consequence that would come from you
doing that action that you would have to
ignore >> in order to do it?
>> in order to do it?
>> Yeah, that sounds like the first thing
you should probably think about.
potentially upsetting other people.
>> Yeah.
>> Getting blamed.
>> Getting blamed. Um
>> yeah, I guess you could say, you know,
[clears throat] um what the degree of
embarrassment you would feel
>> if somebody saw saw you doing that.
>> Yeah. Yeah.
>> Because that's an animal. Like an animal
doesn't care who's watching that.
>> Yeah. Exactly. Exactly. And as I said,
when one is gradually inevitably having
to gradually work towards the eight
precepts, the you would be you would have to be
the you would be you would have to be
giving up to giving [clears throat] in
sorry to the animals pressure.
>> But um the point is even that does not
justify loss of perspective
>> or more loss than than you already
>> Yeah. Yeah. So like you Yeah. Yeah. Of
course. Um furthering of the loss of
perspective. So um
So um
you could then even even ask yourself
say you have a desire to eat something
very specific
>> because also factually you are hungry.
>> Yeah.
>> So the animal mind is factually hungry.
Well the body is hungry. The animal
wants to eat. Um cha is pressuring you
towards food. You know you would know
for a fact that if you were to eat
anything it would actually satisfy the
hunger. Even if it's agreeable stuff,
you don't have to eat stuff that you
hate
and not eat that specific the like extra
specific things that you crave to eat.
>> So on one way you would provide a
satisfaction to the pressure and the
animal even even out of a degree of
weakness but on another way you wouldn't
allow it that that cherry on top that
really want it.
And that principle can actually be
applied in regard to everything
>> you want to again you're not able to
keep the eight precepts. It's too much
pressure. It's too painful. You're
taking on five but not blindly like a
just sort of mindless self-declared
religious Buddhist but actually the one
that wants to train music uh
entertainment. Again, there's specific
things you want out of boredom, out of
anxiety, out of all these unh wholesome
bases that of course you have to deal
with if you actually want to practice
for sortiat.
But now you have to give in to some
extent. It's just too much as we said
before. >> Even then you could start applying the
>> Even then you could start applying the
same principle.
>> So you need a distraction. the mind is
just getting too
too unpleasant, too forceful, too
strong. To what extent you allow that um that
To what extent you allow that um that
desire to be satisfied?
>> Yeah. From the average person's point of
view, that would already be a training
because >> that would be a training. Exactly. Yeah.
>> that would be a training. Exactly. Yeah.
And that's the that's the difference
between keeping the presets and uh
training in them.
>> Your intentions taking them as a
standard. No.
Yes. So inevitably you will feel when
you give in you will feel relieved
to some extent
>> because again you are a craving acting
out of compulsion that gets
appeased. Um so you would feel relieved,
you would feel satisfied.
But if you pay attention to the extent
of your engagement with the sense
objects, try and change try and kind of
relegate the sense object down
>> from the one that you want
>> and force your mind to not quite get
what it wanted. Yeah.
>> Through and through basically
>> and build up on that.